Finding Aid for Department of History of Art (University of Michigan) records, 1946-2013
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Department of History of Art (University of Michigan) records 1946-2013
University of Michigan. Department of History of Art.
1.0 linear feet, 407.7 MB
2013070 Bimu 2
The Department of History of Art was originally established as the Department of Fine Arts in 1911. The collection ranges from 1946 to 2013 and primarily contains personnel files, newsletters and other departmental publications, and meeting minutes of the Executive Committee and Faculty Meetings.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The collection was donated by the Department of History of Art (Donor No. 8397 ) beginning in 1995 with additions in 2012 and 2013.
Periodic additions to the records are expected.
The RG records are open for research except for certain records restricted by statute or university policy. Restricted material includes personnel-related files, including search, review, promotion, and tenure files; student educational records; client/patient records; and records of executive officers of the university.
The RECORD GROUP record group includes restricted material in the following categories:
Personnel Related Records -- Digital files
Before the establishment of a formal department dedicated to the study of the history of art, the topic was taught by a few professors from the Departments of Greek and Latin who incorporated the study of art into their classes. There was no defined art history department until 1911 with the creation of the Department of Fine Arts under the College of Literature, Science, and the Arts. The first chair of the new department was Howard Cross, who received the title as well as appointment as Assistant Professor of Fine Arts. In 1919 the department grew with the addition of Bruce Donaldson as an Instructor of Fine Arts. Over the course of Cross's administration, six graduate degrees in fine arts were awarded, and in 1922 Cross was succeeded by Donaldson as the new chair of the department. It was during Donaldson's administrative years that the department became less focused on the teaching of fine arts and more focused on the integration of classes regarding the history of art. In 1959, the department changed its name to the Department of History of Art.
The Department of History of Art collection is comprised up of three series: Personnel, Publications and Administration.
Subjects:
Art--History.; Art--Study and teaching--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; University of Michigan. Department of History of Art.
- Personnel
  The Personnel series contains files on former faculty members, primarily from the 1950s and 1960s although the content dates from 1946 to 1993.
  - Grigaut, Paul L., 1964-1969 (Box 1)
  - Loehr, Max, 1950-1963 (Box 1)
  - Ludden, Franklin Monroe, 1948-1956, 1961 (Box 1)
  - Maurer, Evan, 1981-1988 (Box 1)
  - Old, Clifton C., 1964-1982, 1993 (Box 1)
  - Phillips, Jr., Kyle Meredith, 1960-1962 (Box 1)
  - Plummer, James, 1946-1963 (Box 1)
    (Includes photo)
  - Stechow, Wolfgang, 1962-1964, 1966 (Box 1)
  - Stern, Harold P., 1963, 1967-1977 (Box 1)
  - Waller, Bret, 1973-1976 (Box 1)
  - Wenley, Archibald G., 1949-1962 (Box 1)
  - Wethey, Harold E., 1946-1986, 2 folders (Box 1)
    (includes photo)
- Publications
  The Publications series includes information about the East Asian Art and Archaeology Newsletter, and issues of the departmental newsletter, flyers for events held by the department, four years of the student publication Helicon Review, and the articles which the History of Art 489 class published regarding their study of Disney World.
  - Department Newsletter, 2004-2009/10 (Box 1)
  - East Asian Art and Archaeology Newsletter
    - Funding, 1983-2001 (Box 1)
    - Grant Correspondence, 1976-2003 (Box 1)
    - Lu-Sheng, Chen Correspondence, 1993 (Box 1)
    - Newsletter Proposal (Box 1)
    - Subscription Services (Box 1)
  - Events, 2007 (Box 1)
  - Helicon Review The University of Michigan Undergraduate History of Art Journal (Volumes II-V), 2009-2012 (Box 1)
  - HISTART 489, 2008 (Box 1)
- Administration [Digital]
  The Administration series contains records of the meeting minutes of the Executive Committee from 2008 to 2013 and Faculty Meetings, 1962-2013. These records are kept digitally. Because of occasional discussions relating to personnel matters, the minutes are governed by a personnel records restriction.
  - Executive Committee Meeting Minutes, 2008-2013 (Box 1)
    [PR Restricted until July 1, 2043 ]
  - Executive Committee Meeting Minutes, 2008-2013 (Box 1)
  - Faculty Meeting Minutes, 2011-2012 (Box 1)
    [PR Restricted until July 1, 2042 ]
  - Faculty Meeting Minutes, 2012-2013 (Box 1)
  - Faculty Meeting Minutes, 1962-1999 (Box 1)
    [PR Restricted until July 1, 2029 ]
Related Material
The East Asian Art and Archaeology Newsletter is cataloged separately under Bentley Library call number FImu C26 E13 N558. The newsletter was originally published under the East Asian Program until 1993 when the program changed its name to Center for Japanese Studies.